Finding aid to the Carole De Saram papers SSC.MS.00794
Sophia Smith Collection
Carole De Saram papers
1970-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
De Saram, Carole
SSC.MS.00794
12 linear feet (8 record cartons, 2 oversize boxes, 1 full document box, 2 half document boxes, and 1 flat file folder)
110 Megabytes (76 files copied from one flash drive)
2 items (2 VHS videocassettes)
Carole De Saram was a feminist activist in the 1970s, working as President of New York City National Organization for Women (NOW) for women's equality in all fields. Her papers include documents, legal information, conference and protest information, and organizational information about the National Organization for Women, as well as photographs, correspondence, and personal documents of Carole De Saram.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Initial accession donated by Carole De Saram in December 2017; subsequent accessions were donated over the course of 2018
Biographical / Historical
Carole De Saram was a feminist activist in the 1970s, working as President of New York City National Organization for Women (NOW) for women's equality in all fields.
Born February 27, 1939 in Queens, New York, De Saram began her career in computing, working on Wall Street at the American Stock Exchange. Inspired by a Wall Street Journal article on women striking for equality, De Saram attended the 1970 March for Equality, and continued working for NOW from that day on. Among her achievements were the woman-led stock exchange takeover, the creation of a women's bank and the Feminist Credit Union, disruption of the US presentation at the 1975 International Women's Conference in Mexico City to protest their choice of US representatives, and numerous incendiary demonstrations against sexist practices of New York City businesses. She became President of NOW NY in 1974, serving two terms, and rose through the ranks at Chemical Bank to become Assistant Vice President while pioneering computer projects with IBM. Written about in "Glamour," investigated by the FBI, and still working in activism in the 2010s, Carole De Saram left her mark on the feminist movement as a whole.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content."
Scope and Contents
The Carole De Saram papers document her role agitating for credit for women in the 1970s and 1980s as part of NYC Now, as well as her participation in International Women's Year in Mexico City. The collection is largely clippings, although original records are interspersed throughout.
The collection includes documents, legal information (FOI requests and responses, lawsuit information, ERA legal proceedings), NOW national conference packets, and protest information, as well as organizational information (membership lists, board meeting notes and proceedings, various referenda) about the National Organization for Women. The collection also includes photographs, correspondence, digital photos and documents related to the Women's Movement compiled by Carole De Saram, and personal documents of Carole De Saram. Also included are videotapes, books, and newspapers relevant to International Women's Year and other feminist issues.
International Women's Year, 1975; Computer media; National Organization for Women--History--Sources; Equal rights amendments--United States--History--Sources; Feminism -- New York(State) -- New York -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Videotapes; Books; De Saram, Carole; De Saram, Carole
- Carole De Saram papers, 2017-S-0067; 10.5 linear feet (8 record cartons, 1 oversize box and 1 flat file folder); 110 Megabytes (76 files copied from flash drive)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes documents, legal information (FOI requests and responses, lawsuit information, ERA legal proceedings), NOW national conference packets, and protest information, as well as organizational information (membership lists, board meeting notes and proceedings, various referenda) about the National Organization for Women. Also includes photographs, correspondence, digital files on the "Women's Movement" compiled by Carole de Saram (2017), and personal documents of Carole De Saram.
  Computer media
  - National NOW newspapers and newsletters, including "Do It Now!", 1970-1980 (Box 1)
  - National NOW Equal Rights Amendment actions, 1970-1978 (Box 1)
  - National NOW Legal Defense & Education Fund, approximately 1975 (Box 1)
  - NOW regional conference records, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - NOW national conference records, 1973-1981 (Box 1)
  - National NOW "Zap" actions, August 1974 (Box 1)
  - National NOW Board records, including notes, correspondence, press releases, and member bios, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - National NOW board split and walk out, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Politics and elections, including women's campaigns and the inauguration of Jimmy Carter, 1974-1984 (Box 2)
    Includes information on elections (both local and national) including the Jimmy Carter Presidential election and inauguration, information about women's participation in politics, NOW elections, NOW publications on which local or national politicans to endorse, and an NBC piece on the history of women's suffrage.
  - Sex discrimination cases, including Congressional hearings, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and NOW Stockholder Action Task Force materials, 1973-1977 (Box 3)
    Includes research and evidence on various cases of gender discrimination, press articles, relevant New York State laws, a FOI request filed by de Saram and its responses, information from Congressional hearings on discrimination cases, and information on corporate stocks.
  - NYNOW Freedom of Information request & responses, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - New York NOW member information, July 26, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Sexual Discrimination Cases, including legislation, action handbooks, events and conferences, 1973-1977 (Box 4)
  - NYNOW FBI files, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
  - NOW New York Chapter: newsletters, membership lists, political campaign materials, and chapter information, 1970-2003; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Equal Rights Amendment: newsletters, State campaign materials, anti-ERA literature, correspondence, and pamphlets, 1974-2004 (Box 6)
  - Publications and Booklets, 1972-2009 (Box 6)
    Various publications on women's rights and the women's movement, including those from NOW, women's history archives, legal guides and reports, and pamphlets.
  - International Women's Year Records: programming, participant biographies, pamphlets, and New York State meeting materials, 1975-1978 (Box 7)
  - Women's Institutions and Groups, including the Redstockings, the New York Feminist Credit Bureau, and the Veteran Feminists of America, 1968-1991 (Box 8)
  - Carole De Saram personal papers: correspondence, photographs, and published articles, 1974-2017 (Box 8)
  - "Women's Movement": presentation materials compiled electronically by Carole De Saram, approximately 1970-2007; 1 items (1 flash drive); 110 Megabytes (76 files copied from one flash drive) (Box 8)
    Primarily scanned photographs and documents. Topics include women's organizations (NOW, IWY), actions, and issues (ERA); conventions; letters, speaking engagements; and personal photographs.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This file contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  - International Women's Year conference and Equal Rights Amendment posters, 1975; 4 items (Folder 1)
- Carole De Saram papers addition, 2018-S-0037; De Saram, Carole; 3.5 linear feet (2 record cartons and 1 large card file)
  Materials include documents, membership lists, and correspondence, and news clippings pertaining to several feminist organizations, including the National Organization for Women, New York NOW, First Women's Bank, Redstockings, and Veteran Feminists of America. This accession also contains legal information, such as FOI requests and responses, class action lawsuit information and testimonials, and clippings about ERA legal proceedings. Information about other influential feminists and political races of the 1970s, photographs, and personal documents of Carole De Saram are also included.
  De Saram, Carole
  - National NOW papers, including administrative and conference information, booklets, Legal Defense Fund materials, photos, and events, 1970-2016; 9 folders (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - New York NOW papers, including chapter information, actions, correspondence, and information on organizational conflicts, 1970-2010; 12 folders (12 folders) (Box 1)
  - New York NOW membership cards, approximately 1970-1980; .5 linear feet (1 large card file box) (Box 3)
  - Veteran Feminists of America papers, including programs, speaking engagements, member information, news, and correspondence, 1998-2017; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 1)
  - Information on feminist organizations, including Redstockings, First Women's Bank, Women's Action Alliance, Women's Survival Space, NY Feminist Credit Union, and information on specific influential women, 1959-2017; 17 folders (17 folders) (Box 1)
  - News clippings and articles on various feminist organizations, 1972-2016; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and articles on women's issues worldwide, 1972-1995; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Political news and campaign information for specific politicians and ERA legislation, 1974-2002; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 2)
  - International Women's Year art festival information, travel documents, notes, and pamphlets, 1975-1976; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - International Women's Year posters, 1975; 6 items (6 posters) (Folder 1)
  - Women's issues and discrimination cases and examples, 1972-2012; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Credit discrimination testimonies, correspondence, and class-action lawsuit information, 1970-1976; 11 folders (11 folders) (Box 2)
  - Legal cases, FOI requests and responses, and IRS documents, 1971-2007; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Personal papers of Carole De Saram, including articles, correspondence, photographs, and speaking engagement information, 1972-2018; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 2)
- Carole De Saram collection of March for Women's Lives materials, 2018-S-0041; 4 folders 3 envelopes and 1 folder in Box 1 of Accession #2018-S-0037 (Carole De Saram papers)
  Email printouts with logistical information about the March, triangle banner, 2 sashes, 5 stickers, and 4 pins. Also includes 4 pins and 2 cards from National NOW conferences and Veteran Feminists of America.
  National Organization for Women -- History
  - March for Women's Lives, Veteran Feminists of America, and NOW pins and cards, 1975-2004; 3 folders (3 envelopes with 8 pins, 2 cards, and 5 stickers) (Box 1)
  - March for Women's Lives printouts and correspondence, 2004; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - March for Women's Lives sashes, triangle banner, 2004; 3 items (3 items added to Folder 1 from Accession #2017-S-0067) (Folder 1)
- Carole De Saram CBS "Broads on Broad Street" collection, 2018-S-0056; .25 linear feet (1 half document box)
  Videotapes
  - CBS pamphlet on women as demographic audience segment, 1973; 1 items (1 booklet) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding "Broads on Broad Street", 1998 April 20; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Video recording, "Broads on Broad St.", 1970 August 16; 1 items (1 Fuji videocassette) (Box 1)
- "The Technology of Orgasm" Dell Williams video and accompanying Wendy Slick correspondence, 2018-S-0055; 1 items (1 VHS videocassette); 1 folders (1 card in a folder)
  One video tape titled, "The Technology of Orgasm," accompanying card addressed to De Saram from Wendy Slick
  Biographical / Historical
  The video tape is of the Dell Williams clip shown at her tribute.
  - Video recording, "The Technology of Orgasm," Dell Williams clip, 2005 October 17; 1 items (1 VHS videocassette) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding "The Technology of Orgasm" from Wendy Slick, approximately 2005 October; 1 folders (1 card) (Box 1)
- Carole De Saram books, 1970-1978; 2018-S-0065; .5 linear feet (1 full letter document box) 6 books and 2 pamphlets (Box 1)
  Books, some low print-run and some signed by the author, all collected by Carol De Saram. Books include Sexual Politics (inscribed by author), Sappho Was a Right-On Woman (inscribed by author), The Rights of Women: The Basic ACLU Guide to a Woman's Rights, Feminist Revolution Redstockings journal, "...To Form a More Perfect Union..." report of the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year, and Constitutional Aspects of the Right to Limit Childbearing report of the United States Commission on Civil Rights. Pamphlets include "Women's Resource Guide to NYC," published by NOW-New York City, and "About the NWHC," published by the National Women's Health Coalition.
- Carole De Saram collection of UN World Conference on Women Mexico City (1975) newspapers, 1975 February-June; 2018-S-0076; .5 linear feet (1 oversize flat box) 23 newspapers (Box 1)
  Newspapers and periodicals collected by De Saram, related to the International Women's Year UN conference in Mexico City. Titles include El Heraldo de Mexico, El Universal, Excelsior, Novedades, and Xilonen, the daily newspaper of the International Women's Year Tribunal